<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<pretext>
  <book xml:id="book-regtes-hypgeo">
    <title>Regular Tessellations and hyperbolic Geometry</title>
    <subtitle>An Approach by Constructions (without Terms and Formulas)</subtitle>


    <chapter xml:id="chapter-regtes">
      <title>Regular Tessellations</title>

        <introduction>
          <p>
            We start by considering which regular tessellations can exist in the Euclidean plane and ask whether there could be other regular tessellations in other geometries. We answer this question (for the time being) with a picture in which the regular tessellations of spherical, Euclidean and hyperbolic geometry are summarized and take this as a motivation to start looking for hyperbolic geometry.
          </p>
        </introduction>

        <section>
          <title>Regular Tessellations in the Euclidean Plane</title>

          <p>
            A <em>tessellation</em> (or <em>tiling</em>) of the Euclidean plane is a covering of the whole plane with one or more geometric shapes, called <em>tiles</em>, with no overlaps an no gaps. The following figures show four selected tessellations of the Euclidean plane.
            <aside>
              More precisely, a tessellation (or tiling) of the Euclidean plane <m>\mathbb{R}^2</m> is a locally finite familiy <m>(U_i)_{i\in I}</m> of bounded open sets <m>U_i\subset \mathbb{R}^2</m> such that these open sets does not intersect pairwise (<m>U_i \cap U_j = \emptyset </m> for all <m>i\neq j \in I</m>) and the union of the closures <m>\overline{U_i}</m>, the tiles, fill the whole plane (i.e. <m>\cup_{i\in I}\overline{U_i} = \mathbb{R}^2</m>). Locally finite means that every circle intersects only with finitely many of the <m>\overline{U_i}</m>
            </aside> 
          </p>
          <p>
            <sidebyside widths="49% 49%" margins="0% 0%">
              <figure xml:id="semiregular_3_3_4_3_4_tessellation">
                <caption>The semiregular <m>(3, 3, 4, 3, 4)</m>-tessellation</caption>
                <image source="images/semiregular_3_3_4_3_4_tessellation.svg"></image>
              </figure>
              <figure xml:id="cairo_tessellation">
                <caption>The Cairo pentagonal tessellation</caption>
                <image source="images/cairo_tessellation.svg"></image>
              </figure>
            </sidebyside>
            <sidebyside  widths="49% 49%" margins="0% 0%">
              <figure xml:id="semiregular_4_6_12_tessellation">
                <caption>The semiregular <m>(4, 6, 12)</m>-tessellation</caption>
                <image source="images/semiregular_4_6_12_tessellation.svg"></image>
              </figure>
              <figure xml:id="non_side_by_side_square_tessellation">
                <caption>A tesselation with squares</caption>
                <image source="images/square_non_side_by_side_tessellation.svg"></image>
              </figure>
            </sidebyside>
          </p>
          <p>
            The tessellations in <xref ref="semiregular_3_3_4_3_4_tessellation"/> consist of regular <m>3</m>- and <m>4</m>-gons. <xref ref="semiregular_4_6_12_tessellation"/> consist of regular <m>4</m>-, <m>6</m>- and <m>12</m>-gons. Tessellations consisting of regular polygons are called  <em>semiregular tessellations</em>. In the Euclidean plane there are exactly eight semiregular tesselations (see <xref ref="appendix-semregtes"/> for a more precise definition and a proof).
          </p>

          <p>
            The tessellation in <xref ref="cairo_tessellation"/> is called the <em>Cairo pentagonal tessellation</em>, since it can be found on streets in Cairo and since it consists of congruent pentagons. The Cairo pentagonal tessellation is dual to the semiregular <m>(3, 3, 4, 3, 4)</m>-tessellation in <xref ref="semiregular_3_3_4_3_4_tessellation"/> (you get it by connecting the centers of adjacent tiles).
          </p>
          <p>
          <activity number="1">
            <statement>
              <ol>
                <li><p>Construct the semiregular <m>(3, 3, 4, 3, 4)</m>-tessellation in <xref ref="semiregular_3_3_4_3_4_tessellation"/>, e.g. with GeoGebra.</p></li>
                <li xml:id="exercise-cairo-tessellation"><p>Construct the Cairo pentagonal tessellationin <xref ref="cairo_tessellation"/> starting from the <m>(3, 3, 4, 3, 4)</m>-tessellation, e.g. with GeoGebra.</p></li>
              </ol>
            </statement>
            <hint>
              In the <m>(3, 3, 4, 3, 4)</m>-tessellation, two edges of a triangle coincide with an edge of a adjacent square, the third edge coincides with an edge of an adjacend triangle.
            </hint>
          </activity>
        </p>
          <p>
            Even it is very interesting (and not easy at all) to understand tessellations in general, we will focus only on the so called regular ressellations. For this, we first remember the concept of the regular <m>n</m>-gon. In the following, <m>n</m> denotes a natural number <m>\geq 3</m>.
            <definition>
              A <em>regular <m>n</m>-gon</em> or <em>regular polygon</em> in the Euclidean plane is a polygon consisting of <m>n</m> sides that is equiangular (all interior angles between neighboring sides are equal) and equilateral (all sides have the same length).
              <figure xml:id="regular_polygon">
                <caption>Regular <m>5</m>-gon</caption>
                <image source="images/test_image.svg" width="50%"></image>
              </figure>
            </definition>
            <lemma>
              The <m>n</m> vertices of a regular <m>n</m>-gon lie on a circle. The <em>center</em> angle, i.e. the angle between two neighoring vertices with the center of the circle, equals <m>360° / n</m>.  The <em>interior</em> angle (the interior angle between to neighboring sides) equals <m>180° - \frac{360°}{n}</m>.
            </lemma>
            <activity number="2">
              <statement>
                <p>Show that the interior angle of a regular <m>n</m>-gon equals <m>180° - \frac{360°}{n}</m>.</p>
              </statement>
            </activity>
          </p>
          <p>
            <definition>
              A <em>regular <m>n</m>-tessellation</em> of the Euclidean plane is a side-by-side covering with regular <m>n</m>-gons of the whole plane with no overlaps and no gaps. Side-by-side means, that every side of every regular <m>n</m>-gon coincides with exactly one side of another regular <m>n</m>-gon. For brevity we often omit the <m>n</m> and write <em>regular tesselation</em>.
            </definition>
            In the Euclidean plane we all know the three following regular tessellations:
            <sidebyside>
              <figure xml:id="regular_3_6_tessellation">
                <caption>The regular <m>(3,6)</m>-tessellation of the Euc</caption>
                <image source="images/test_image.svg" width="50%"></image>
              </figure>
              <figure xml:id="regular_4_4_tessellation">
                <caption>The regular <m>(4,4)</m>-tessellation of the Euc</caption>
                <image source="images/test_image.svg" width="50%"></image>
              </figure>
              <figure xml:id="regular_6_3_tessellation">
                <caption>The regular <m>(6,3)</m>-tessellation of the Euc</caption>
                <image source="images/test_image.svg" width="50%"></image>
              </figure>
            </sidebyside>
            We will show that there are no other regular tessellations of the Eulidean plane. For this we first formulate some basic propoerties of regular tesselations:
            <lemma>
              <p>In a regular <m>n</m>-tessellation
                <ol>
                  <li><p>all regular <m>n</m>-gons are congruent.</p></li>
                  <li><p>the number of joining <m>n</m>-gons in a vertice is the same for every vertice.</p></li>
                </ol>
              </p>
              <proof>
                <ol>
                  <li>
                    <p>It is clear that two regular <m>n</m>-gons which have a common side are congruent. Let <m>A</m> and <m>A'</m> be two regular <m>n</m>-gons. Since the tessellation fills the whole plane it is possible to find a sequence <m>A=A_1, A_2, ..., A_k=A'</m> of <m>n</m>-gons such that two subsequent <m>n</m>-gons share a common side. Hence <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are congruent.</p>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                    <p>Let <m>m</m> be the number of <m>n</m>-gons coming together in any corner. Since all occuring <m>n</m>-gons are congruent, the interior angle of any of these <m>n</m>-gon must equal <m>\frac{360°}{m}</m>. Or, inversely, the number <m>m</m> of congruent <m>n</m>-gons coming together in any vertice must equal <m>360°/\alpha</m>, where <m>\alpha</m> is the interior angle of the congruent <m>n</m>-gons.</p>
                  </li>
                </ol>
              </proof>
            </lemma>
          </p>
          In the following we denote by <m>m\geq 3</m> the number of <m>n</m>-gons comming together in every vertice of a regular tessellation and denote such a regular tesselation as a regular <m>(n,m)</m>-tessellation.
          <theorem>
            <p>
              For a regular <m>(n,m)</m>-tessellation of the Euclidean plane, the equation <m>\frac{1}{n} + \frac{1}{m} = \frac{1}{2}</m> holds. The only solutions (for natural <m>n,m\geq 3</m>) to this equation are the <m>(n,m)</m>-pairs <m>(3,6)</m>, <m>(4,4)</m> and <m>(6,3)</m>. Hence the three tessellations shown in <xref ref="regular_3_6_tessellation"/>, <xref ref="regular_4_4_tessellation"/> and <xref ref="regular_6_3_tessellation"/> are the only regular tessallation in the Eulidean plane.
            </p>
            <proof>
              <p>The interior angle of a regular <m>n</m>-gon in the Euclidean plane equals <m>\alpha := 180° - \frac{360°}{n}</m>. Since <m>m</m> regular <m>n</m>-gons are coming together in a corner, we have <m>360° = m\cdot \alpha = m\cdot ( 180° - \frac{360°}{n})</m>. After dividing by <m>m\cdot 360°</m> and bringing <m>\frac{1}{n}</m> to the other side, we have <m>\frac{1}{n} + \frac{1}{m} = \frac{1}{2}</m></p>.
              <figure xml:id="explaining_the_proof_of_the_equation">
                <caption>TODO</caption>
                <image source="images/test_image.svg" width="50%"></image>
              </figure>
              <p>As next, we show that the <m>(n,m)</m>-pairs <m>(3,6)</m>, <m>(4,4)</m> and <m>(6,3)</m> are the only solutions to this equation.</p>
            </proof>
          </theorem>
          <p>
            To understand the solutions of <m>\frac{1}{n} + \frac{1}{m} = \frac{1}{2}</m> for <m>n, m\geq 3</m> we scetch the follwoing matrix:
            <figure xml:id="n_m_matrix_with_values">
              <caption>TODO</caption>
              <image source="images/test_image.svg" width="50%"></image>
            </figure>
            To obtain <m>\frac{1}{n} + \frac{1}{m} >= \frac{1}{2}</m>, either <m>n \seq 6</m> or <m> m \sme6 </m> must hold. Hence for <m>n, m >= 6</m> we always have <m>\frac{1}{n} + \frac{1}{m} \sm \frac{1}{2}</m>.
            With this in mind we find out that there are exactly five <m>(n,m)</m>-pairs with <m>\frac{1}{n} + \frac{1}{m} > \frac{1}{2}</m> and exactly three  <m>(n,m)</m>-pairs with <m>\frac{1}{n} + \frac{1}{m} = \frac{1}{2}</m> and infinitely many  <m>(n,m)</m>-pairs with <m>\frac{1}{n} + \frac{1}{m}  \frac{1}{2}</m>. These three types corresponds to the spherical, Euclidean and hyperbolic tessellations, which are shown for <m>3 \leq n, m \leq 8</m> in the following figure:
            <figure xml:id="n_m_matrix_with_tessellations">
              <caption>TODO</caption>
              <image source="images/test_image.svg" width="50%"></image>
            </figure>
            The five solutions with ??? are the five ???, projected to the sphere. Hence, the geometry on the sphere is the geometry where regular tesselation with ??? occurs.
            The natural question which occurs now is, wheter there is also a geometry where the infinitely many solutions with ??? are regular tesselations. The answer is yes: hyerbolic geometry. In the remaining of the text we will work out this very interesting and beautiful geometry. In the end we will be able to draw all regular tesselations as shown in ???.
          </p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="chapter-eucgeo">
        <title>Euclidean Geometry from another Perspective</title>

        <introduction>
          <p>
            We deal with Euclidean line reflections and recognize that these are something like the atomic building blocks of Euclidean geometry.
          </p>
        </introduction>
    </chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="chapter-hypgeo1">
        <title>Hyperbolic Points, Lines and Angles</title>

        <introduction>
          <p>
            We define points, lines and angles in the Poincaré model of hyperbolic geometry.
          </p>
        </introduction>

        
    </chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="chapter-circinv">
        <title>Circle Inversion</title>

        <introduction>
          <p>
            We define the circle inversion in the Euclidean plane and work out important constructions and properties of this surprising and at the same time intuitive mapping.
          </p>
        </introduction>
    </chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="chapter-hypgeo2">
        <title>Hyperbolic line reflections, perpendicular Bisectors and Circles</title>

        <introduction>
          <p>
            We learn how the hyperbolic line through two hyperbolic points can be constructed by circle inversion. Then we define the reflection on a hyperbolic line - of course also with circle inversion. With the tool of hyperbolic line reflection we are then able to introduce the hyperbolic perpendicular bisector and a kind of hyperbolic distance. We use this to define hyperbolic circles and to classify them completely.
          </p>
        </introduction>
    </chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="chapter-hypregtes">
        <title>Hyperbolic regular Tessellations</title>

        <introduction>
          <p>
            We construct the hyperbolic regular tessellations - with what has been worked out so far, this is pleasantly simple and intuitive.
          </p>
        </introduction>
    </chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="chapter-spheuchypgeo">
        <title>Spherical, Euclidean and hyperbolic Geometriy</title>

        <introduction>
          <p>
            We compare essential properties of spherical, Euclidean and hyperbolic geometry.
          </p>
        </introduction>
    </chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="chapter-histhypgeo">
        <title>History of hyperbolic Geometry</title>

        <introduction>
          <p>
            We take a look at selected aspects of the history of hyperbolic geometry.
          </p>
        </introduction>
    </chapter>

    <appendix xml:id="appendix-semregtes">
      <title>Semiregular Tessellations in the Euclidean Plane</title>

      <introduction>
          <p>
            We show that there are exactly eight semiregular tessellations in the Euclidean plane.
          </p>
        </introduction>
    </appendix>

    <appendix xml:id="appendix-linref">
      <title>Line Reflections are the atomic building Blocks of Euclidean Geometry</title>

      <introduction>
          <p>
            We show that every distance preserving map in the Euclidean plane is a product of at most three line reflections.
          </p>
        </introduction>
    </appendix>


  </book>
</pretext>